<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-05-29T12:58:38+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Pete Ashton’s Art</title><subtitle>How he became, and was, an artist, 2006–2021&lt;br /&gt;(slowly updating and annotating during 2024)</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Coronavirus Press Conferences</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/coronavirus_press_conferences/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coronavirus Press Conferences" /><published>2021-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Coronavirus%20Press%20Conferences</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/coronavirus_press_conferences/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/Covid_Press_Conferences_cover_photo.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Published as a:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="/assets/docs/Covid_Press_Conferences_-_Web.pdf">Free PDF download</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.lulu.com/en/gb/shop/pete-ashton/coronavirus-press-conferences-march-to-december-2020/paperback/product-qwed7n.html">£20 paperback, unlimited edition</a></li>
  <li>£50 hardback, signed limited edition - email to order pete@peteashton.com</li>
</ul>

<p>A copy has been purchased for the <a href="https://thenewartgallerywalsall.org.uk/collections-library/library/">New Art Gallery Walsall’s Artist Books Collection</a>, which is nice.</p>

<p><em><a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLqHKtAbFyKz5iB9nY94YIIxJGCXXY7JHy">Source videos were downloaded from here.</a></em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/Covid_Press_Conferences_book_photo.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/Covid_Press_Conferences_spine.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/hvv3snYziHk?si=7YwCXbceaqNGqeQM" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<hr />

<p><img src="/assets/images/coronavirus_press_conferences_sample.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/coronavirus_press_conferences_sample_5.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h3 id="from-the-books-afterword">From the book’s afterword:</h3>

<p>In March 2020 the UK government began regular press briefings about the emerging coronavirus pandemic. These took place at a podium at Number 10 Downing Street where a minister, sometimes the Prime Minister, spoke directly to a static camera for five or so minutes before introducing advisors and taking questions.</p>

<p>These ministers had not expected to be dealing with this. They had been chosen for their belief in Brexit and their loyalty to Boris Johnson ahead of any experience or competence in running their departments. The ideological purge of politicians and civil servants by the Johnson regime in 2019 had left the UK government ill-equipped by any standards.</p>

<p>It’s a year into the pandemic as I write this and over 100,000 people have died in the UK. Vaccines are being rolled out but the country feels dazed and confused, battered by mixed messages and contradictory instructions.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/coronavirus_press_conferences_sample_2.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>This book covers the 89 press conferences uploaded to the Number 10 YouTube channel in 2020.</p>

<p>Watching them I was struck by how young they look. Dominic Raab, covering for Johnson when he was hospitalised with Covid, looks startled and terrified, while Matt Hancock has the air of an earnest son, very keen to get things right. Grant Shapps looks fresh from scraping a passing grade in his GCSEs, while Rishi Sunak reads his scripts in the manner of someone who definitely didn’t write them.</p>

<p>And then there’s Johnson, the leader who hates to lead, hates to give bad news, hates to make hard decisions. His ruthless self-interest has always been masked by jocular bluster, but it is particularly ill-suited for this. We don’t need feel-good optimism. We need a framework to live and work in this new reality. We need honesty and clarity and compassion.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/coronavirus_press_conferences_sample_3.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>The speaking-to-a-fixed-camera trope, denoting seriousness and directness, lends itself well to the process I’ve employed in these artworks. The background is static while the speaker is animated. Extracting a shot every five seconds, I merge 100 or so frames using a focus-stacking algorithm, pulling out the sharpest points and smoothing the final result.</p>

<p>The algorithm is not designed for this, so the results are always interesting. Teeth and eyes multiply, dark hair dominates, and white shirts bleach the image centre into a void. Later someone remembers their accessibility obligations and a signer is introduced, transformed into a manic pixie, all hands and grins.</p>

<p>The result is a blur of chaotic emptiness. This is what it feels like to watch the Coronavirus Press Conferences</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/coronavirus_press_conferences_sample_4.jpg" alt="" /></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Pandemic" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A book of focus-stacked images of the 89 press briefings from No 10 Downing Street in 2020.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/coronavirus_press_conferences_t.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/coronavirus_press_conferences_t.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Extreme Noticing under Lockdown</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/extremenoticing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Extreme Noticing under Lockdown" /><published>2020-09-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Extreme%20Noticing%20under%20Lockdown</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/extremenoticing/"><![CDATA[<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/443903570?h=844f3af1fe&amp;title=0&amp;byline=0&amp;portrait=0" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Video presentation for the <a href="https://www.4wcop.org/">4th World Congress on Psychogeography</a> 2020 by myself with <a href="http://fionacullinan.com/">Fiona Cullinan</a> and <a href="http://andyhowlett.co.uk/">Andy Howlett</a>, the founder members of Walkspace.</p>

<p><a href="http://walkspace.uk/2020/09/walkspace-at-the-4wcop/">Walkspace archive page</a>, with video of the subsequent panel discussion.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Walking" /><category term="Talks" /><category term="Pandemic" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Video presentation of art-walking in Stirchley during the pandemic, for 4WCoP.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/extremenoticing_t.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/extremenoticing_t.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Boris Johnson speeches</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/boris-speeches/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Boris Johnson speeches" /><published>2020-05-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-05-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Boris%20Johnson&apos;s%20Speeches</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/boris-speeches/"><![CDATA[<p>Three speeches by our then Prime Minister made directly to camera. I took frames from these recordings and fed them through a image averaging and/or focus stacking algorithms in an attempt to make sense of them, and maybe see through the bluster to his soul.</p>

<h1 id="hands">Hands</h1>

<p><em>May 2020</em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/Boris_Hands_HD.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>A response to watching Prime Minister Boris Johnson’s address to the nation on May 10th, 2020. This was a moment when the seriousness of the situation threatened to overtake optimistic bluster but didn’t quite succeed.</p>

<p>I was struck by his hands, how they never stopped moving, so I put frames from the speech through an image merging algorithm to draw them out. A ghostly Johnson face was added as a transparency to top it off.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bjvRhrJqNHI">Original video</a></p>

<h1 id="september-22nd">September 22nd</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/images/PM22Sep.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>A response to watching Prime Minister Boris Johnson’s address to the nation on September 22nd, 2020. This was another turning point, as the virus started to surge into the autumn after a summer of lessened restrictions.</p>

<p>I was struck by his hands had now stopped moving, compared to April. The gravity of the situation had finally hit home.</p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/HyG_HYTk3hI">Original video</a></p>

<h1 id="brexmas">Brexmas</h1>

<p><em>December 2020</em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/Brexmas.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>A response to watching Prime Minister Boris Johnson’s address to the nation on December 24th 2020 after the Brexit trade agreement was finalised.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pC7ofw33XbQ">Original video</a></p>

<h1 id="bonus-partygate">BONUS: Partygate</h1>

<p><em>March 2023</em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/BJ Partygate Questioning stddev.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>A response to watching Prime Minister Boris Johnson’s answering questions about the Partygate scandal in which his soul appears to pour out of his face onto the table.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Pandemic" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Merging Boris Johnson's pandemic addresses to the nation.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Brexmas_t.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Brexmas_t.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Waiting for Trump</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/waiting-for-trump/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Waiting for Trump" /><published>2020-04-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Waiting%20for%20Trump</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/waiting-for-trump/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/WFT_1.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Donald Trump was notorious for being late to his Coronavirus press briefings, then suddenly arriving without warning. I discovered that the live streams began on time and consisted of a static wide shot of the reporters waiting patiently, before zooming in on the tardy president. In this particular video the reporters are waiting for 1 hour 13 minutes.</p>

<p>There are two versions. The first, above, is made with the focus-stacking algorithm which compares differences between frames and draws out sharper edges. The second, below, is a standard averaging of all frames, mimicking a long exposure photograph.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/WFT_2.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PvbkHLr6dTw">Original video</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Pandemic" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Compressing the time reporters spent waiting for Donald Trump to arrive for a press conference.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/WFT_t.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/WFT_t.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Manifestation of the Desire for Order in a Newly Chaotic World</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/manifestation-desire-order/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Manifestation of the Desire for Order in a Newly Chaotic World" /><published>2020-04-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Manifestation%20of%20the%20Desire%20for%20Order%20in%20a%20Newly%20Chaotic%20World</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/manifestation-desire-order/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/Manifestation_of_the_Desire_for_Order_in_a_Newly_Chaotic_World.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>After a hectic and traumatising March of full days and sleepless nights, I suddenly found myself furloughed in April and legally unable to work. This rapid stop was highly discombobulating and, while too exhausted to do anything substantial, I searched for something, anything, to do.</p>

<p>Realising we were going to be spending a lot of time at home and in the garden, I set to work constructing a sunshade. I didn’t put much thought into the design and the emergent 2 metre square floating in the air quickly caught the attention of my neighbours.</p>

<p>It seemed to be an expression of something deep in my soul, an articulation of loss, a desire for order. It had conceptually transformed into my first piece of lockdown art.</p>

<p>The piece was exhibited in the back garden until September 2020 when it was replaced with a geodesic dome. It has since been integrated into the shed awning extension by the rabbit run.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Pandemic" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sculpture for the start of furlough.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Manifestation_of_the_Desire_for_Order_in_a_Newly_Chaotic_World_t.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/Manifestation_of_the_Desire_for_Order_in_a_Newly_Chaotic_World_t.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Most of Stoned Moon</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/most-of-stoned-moon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Most of Stoned Moon" /><published>2019-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Most%20of%20Stoned%20Moon</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/most-of-stoned-moon/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/most-of-stoned-moon.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>During research for the 1972 project I came across a series of lithographs by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Rauschenberg">Robert Rauschenberg</a> made in response to the Apollo 11 landing entitled <a href="https://www.rauschenbergfoundation.org/art/series/stoned-moon-edition">Stoned Moon</a>. I found 16 of them online and crushed them together using a focus-stacking algorithm.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/peteashton/49019838706/">The work lives on Flickr</a> where higher resolution versions of are available to download.</p>

<p>A print of this work was submitted to the <a href="https://www.artefactstirchley.co.uk/">Artefact</a> Winter Open, exhibited from Dec 5th 2019 to Jan 31st 2020.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="1972project" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A digital collage of Robert Rauschenberg lithographs]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/most-of-stoned-moon_t.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/most-of-stoned-moon_t.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">1972 v0.1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/1972-v0.1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="1972 v0.1" /><published>2019-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/1972-v1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/1972-v0.1/"><![CDATA[<p>The hardest part of <a href="https://art.peteashton.com/1972/">The 1972 Project</a> was starting it, so I decided to make a film in a fortnight and present it show it to people regardless of its quality. No procrastination, no tweaking, just get it out there, and once it’s done, move on to the next thing.</p>

<p>It was presented at The Magic Cinema at Artefact, Stirchley, on November 27th 2019, launching the project.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UzBvUlPccd4?si=p2PuZFGuYFT3S4W7" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h2 id="transcript">Transcript</h2>

<p><em>Punctuation was amended to coax the text-to-speech algorithm into phrasing more coherently and has been left intact because it amuses me to do so.</em></p>

<h3 id="part-1">Part 1</h3>

<p>As we reach the end of the second decade of the third millennium, two things are apparent. The world has, once again, gone bat fuck crazy, and the era of the internet, is at its zenith.</p>

<p>Some have speculated that these two things are related, and that in order to lance the boil something needs to happen. But beyond sticking plasters and hand-wringing, no-one seems to know what.</p>

<p>In the West, at least, our leaders hark back to past glories through populist blinkers. For better or worse, the left longs for new deals and welfare states while the right dreams of empire and divine right.</p>

<p>Meanwhile the culture of the 21st century is stuck in the 20th, nostalgically regurgitating futures from a bygone age. Everything new is old again. The future is the past with a knowing wink.</p>

<p>Does this matter? Well, the 20th Century did have some unfortunate side effects. The climate is fucked for a start.</p>

<p>And the last few decades of neoliberal economics do seem to have made a handful of people absurdly wealthy, to the detriment of everyone else.</p>

<p>We can’t keep doing the same old thing and hoping it all works out. But imagining a different future, one that is truly of the future, seems to be getting harder and harder.</p>

<p>Futurists used to be visionaries, dismantling the common-sense of the present, to figure out what might happen next. What are the futurists of today thinking?</p>

<p>In January 2019, Jeff Bezos, boss of Amazon and world’s richest man, presented his dream, his endgame. All that he has done turned out to be in the service of giant space stations, orbiting the Earth and housing 10s of thousands of people. His space rocket company, Blue Origin, would lay the foundations for this epic technological feat, saving humanity and the Earth, whilst ensuring progress continued unimpeded.</p>

<p>This seems radically futuristic, but the idea is actually fifty years old. In 1969, Gerry O’Neill, a professor at Princeton University, asked his students, faced with the optimism of the Apollo programme and the dire state of the Vietnam War, to consider whether the surface of a planet is really the right place for an expanding technological civilization. They convinced him it wasn’t, and he spent the 1970s thinking about space colonies.</p>

<p>In 1972 the final Apollo mission, number 17, went to the moon and the programme was cancelled. While the just-announced Space Shuttle was in development NASA searched furtively for a new mission to fill the yawning gap left by Apollo. What could come next?</p>

<p>This was Gerry O’Neill’s chance, and in 1975 he convened the first of three Conferences on Space Colonization, resulting in the now famous paintings of gigantic space stations populated by ordinary looking humans. This was to be America’s new frontier. Not shiny and militaristic, but green and Earth like. A new world for the next generation of pioneers.</p>

<p>Of course these never came to pass. The political and economic will was not there, and Gerry O’Neill went back to teaching at Princeton, where, circa 1985, a young Star Trek fan called Jeff Bezos, whose high-school valedictorian speech was an earnest call for space colonisation, becomes his student. The rest of Bezos’s life, it seems, will be dedicated to fulfilling O’Neill’s dream.</p>

<p>But Bezos hasn’t tried to update these designs. He hasn’t merged them with the last fifty years of technological and social change. He sees them as the solution to our problems but either our problems haven’t changed, or O’Neill’s solutions are eternal.</p>

<p>Maybe O’Neill was fifty years ahead of his time and it’s only now the world has caught up that Bezos can make it happen. Maybe O’Neill was a true futurist, and Bezos, king of the supply chain, is the pragmatist.</p>

<p>It’s a nice idea, but I think something was happening in the early 70s, specifically around 1972, that put us on a path that we seem incapable of changing.</p>

<h3 id="part-2">Part 2</h3>

<p>Seventy two things that will be fifty years old in 2022, somewhat arbitrarily picked from Wikipedia pages about 1972.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Animation studio Aardman Animation.</li>
  <li>The first pocket calculator the HP-35.</li>
  <li>James Lovelock’s Gaia hypothesis.</li>
  <li>Actor and Tom Watson impersonator Nick Frost.</li>
  <li>Direct Rule in Northern Ireland.</li>
  <li>The pornographic movie Deep Throat.</li>
  <li>The Watergate Break-in.</li>
  <li>Actor Cameron Diaz.</li>
  <li>The announcement of the Space Shuttle program.</li>
  <li>Actor comedian and tall person Peter Serafinowicz.</li>
  <li>British credit card brand Access.</li>
  <li>Second wave feminist magazine Spare Rib.</li>
  <li>Actor Karl Urban.</li>
  <li>Comedian and actress Maya Rudolph.</li>
  <li>Nights in White Satin by the Moody Blues.</li>
  <li>Post-Stonewall campaigning newspaper Gay News.</li>
  <li>David Hockney’s Portrait of an Artist.</li>
  <li>Singer Liam Gallagher.</li>
  <li>Actor Toni Collette.</li>
  <li>Bob Fosse’s film Cabaret.</li>
  <li>Hysterical disaster movie The Poseidon Adventure.</li>
  <li>Soccer player Zinedine Zidane.</li>
  <li>Historical pop song American Pie.</li>
  <li>The World Trade Center.</li>
  <li>Proto-electronica banger Popcorn.</li>
  <li>The Blue Marble photograph of Earth from space.</li>
  <li>Ernő Goldfinger’s Trellick Tower.</li>
  <li>First video game console the Magnavox Odyssey.</li>
  <li>Neil Young’s Heart of Gold.</li>
  <li>Hillbilly-phobic movie Deliverance.</li>
  <li>Smutty sit-com Are You Being Served.</li>
  <li>Future world president Dwayne Johnson.</li>
  <li>Purveyor of high quality television… and breasts, HBO.</li>
  <li>Popular chanteuses and professional ginger, Geri Halliwell.</li>
  <li>Delightful mixed-use development the Brunswick Centre.</li>
  <li>Hippy-centric intercourse-manual The Joy of Sex.</li>
  <li>American game show The Price Is Right.</li>
  <li>Tall ball bouncer Shaquille O’Neal.</li>
  <li>Actress Octavia Spencer.</li>
  <li>Spewer of truths, Frankie Boyle.</li>
  <li>Holistic analysis of capitalism, The Limits to Growth.</li>
  <li>Rapper Busta Rhymes.</li>
  <li>Animated movie Fritz the Cat.</li>
  <li>People’s Republic of Bangladesh.</li>
  <li>Television presenter Claudia Winkleman.</li>
  <li>Scottish actor Ewen Bremner.</li>
  <li>The Munich Olympics massacre.</li>
  <li>The Notorious B.I.G..</li>
  <li>Democratic politician Beto O’Rourke.</li>
  <li>Sexy-ish film Last Tango in Paris.</li>
  <li>Right-wing politician Priti Patel.</li>
  <li>John Berger’s Ways of Seeing.</li>
  <li>The television series M_A_S*H.</li>
  <li>Actress Thandie Newton.</li>
  <li>The first treaty of the Strategic Arms Limitation Talks.</li>
  <li>Bloody Sunday.</li>
  <li>Ceylon is renamed Sri Lanka.</li>
  <li>Actress Jennifer Garner.</li>
  <li>Artist and musician Björk.</li>
  <li>The catalogue retailer Argos.</li>
  <li>Astronaut Tim Peake.</li>
  <li>Andrei Tarkovsky’s Solaris.</li>
  <li>Actor Ben Affleck.</li>
  <li>The computer game Pong.</li>
  <li>Francis Ford Coppola’s Godfather.</li>
  <li>The National Express coach company.</li>
  <li>John Craven’s Newsround.</li>
  <li>Child-actor survivor and professional nerd Wil Wheaton.</li>
  <li>The demolition of the Pruitt–Igoe housing project heralding the death of modernism.</li>
  <li>Stewart Brand’s Last Whole Earth Catalogue wins the National Book Award.</li>
  <li>The launch of Apollo 17, the final mission to the moon.</li>
  <li>Creator of this video, artist Pete Ashton.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="part-3">Part 3</h3>

<p>My name is Pete Ashton and I am an artist based in Birmingham, a city in the north west of Europe.</p>

<p>1972 is the overarching title and theme of my work for the next three years, culminating on my fiftieth birthday in September 2022.</p>

<p>Over the next three years I will be making work about this half-century, exploring how it came to be, why we can’t seem to see a future whilst within it, and what that future might look like.</p>

<p>Some of the work will be serious and didactic as fuck. Some will be daft and seemingly irrelevant. Some will be collaborative, while other work will be more personal.</p>

<p>The scope of this project is absurdly large, so I plan to use my life and my obsessions as a framework. As a child I was obsessed with NASA’s space programme. As a teen and into my 20s comic books led me deep into the counterculture and underground publishing. And in my 30s I made my home on the Internet with blogging and the early social media platforms.</p>

<p>I believe these three things are deeply inter twing guld and I think may provide some useful answers.</p>

<p>Please join me on this journey of exploration and illumination which I promise is not a mid-life crisis. Honest.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Talks" /><category term="1972project" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A first stab at figuring some stuff out.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/blue-marble_t.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/blue-marble_t.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The 1972 Project</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/1972/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 1972 Project" /><published>2019-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/1972-project</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/1972/"><![CDATA[<p><em>The coronavirus pandemic, of course, threw numerous spanners in the works, not least rendering my brain incompetent during most of 2020-22. I do hope to revive this project in some form though.</em></p>

<p><strong>The 1972 Project</strong> is the overarching title of work I will be making between November 2019 and September 2022.</p>

<p>I was born in 1972 and the date has haunted me throughout my life, appearing on IDs, forms and drop-down menus. Yet I have no memory of that year and no real sense of what happened in that era because I was a baby.</p>

<p>Thinking this a curious thing I decided to explore 1972 both as the seed of myself but also as the seed of my world. It turns out that it’s quite plausible to see the early 70s as a turning point in western society and it tracks nicely with my growing up.</p>

<p>My 1972 artworks will evolve and iterate over the next three years resulting in something around the date of my 50th birthday. This feels like a more interesting thing to do that a mid-life crisis.</p>

<p>The works will be documented here.</p>

<h2 id="1972-version-01">1972 version 0.1</h2>

<p><em>November 2019</em></p>

<p>A short film made to start the project, ensuring that it begins. Screened at The Magic Cinema, Artefact, November 27th 2019</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong><a href="https://art.peteashton.com/1972-v0.1/">Archive page with transcript</a></strong></li>
  <li><strong><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UzBvUlPccd4">Video on YouTube</a></strong></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="most-of-stoned-moon">Most of Stoned Moon</h2>

<p><em>December 2019</em></p>

<p>A digital collage for the Artefact Xmas Show, 5-21 December.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong><a href="https://art.peteashton.com/most-of-stoned-moon/">Archive page</a></strong></li>
  <li><strong><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/peteashton/49019838706/">Image on Flickr</a></strong></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="arpanet-and-the-hippies-working-title">ARPANET and the Hippies (working title)</h2>

<p><em>cancelled due to pandemic but hope to revive in some form</em></p>

<p>A five week exhibition at Artefact, Stirchley, of materials gathered during research into Stewart Green’s influence on the development of the Internet.</p>

<h2 id="the-final-work">The final work</h2>

<p><em>September 2022</em></p>

<p>I have no idea what form this will take. If you are an arts organisation (or similar) and are interested in hosting / exhibiting / supporting the final work in this project, please get in touch.</p>

<h2 id="bookmarks">Bookmarks</h2>

<p>All web materials gathered for this project are <a href="https://raindrop.io/peteashton/1972-project-44379332">bookmarked on Raindrop</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="1972project" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Making work about the period from the last moon landing to my 50th birthday.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/1972_t.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/1972_t.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Rivers of the World 2019</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/rotw-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rivers of the World 2019" /><published>2019-06-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-06-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Rivers-of-the-World-2019</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/rotw-2019/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://art.peteashton.com/assets/images/rotw2019-cameras.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://riversoftheworld.org">Rivers of the World</a> has been run by the Thames Festival since 2006, teaming up London schools with schools in cities around the world to learn about each other by exploring their local rivers. I worked for the project in 2018 when it expanded out of London for the first time and in 2019 returned to Worcester to run workshops at schools that were twinned with schools in Nairobi, Kenya.</p>

<p>This year I proposed using a camera obscura building workshop and for the pupils to use their hand-held cameras as viewing devices to find interesting and overlooked views in their school. The cameras were built from <a href="http://art.peteashton.com/assets/docs/camera_obscura_template.pdf">a simple template</a> I designed using cardboard boxes, tracing paper and cheap plastic magnifying glasses.</p>

<p>To tie the workshop to their twin school in Kenya I asked the teachers to take lots of photos while on an exchange visit earlier in the year which I gave to the students as inspiration. I asked them to look for shapes patterns - triangles, circles, etc - rather than objects, and then photograph them with digital cameras.</p>

<p>I then documented the cameras they’d built and used all the matrials to produce a banner artwork which, at time of writing, will be exhibited on the bank of the Thames in London later this year.</p>

<p><img src="http://art.peteashton.com/assets/images/rotw2019-montage.jpg" alt="" /><br />
Left to right: Nunnery Wood, Tudor Grange.</p>

<h2 id="nunnery-wood">Nunnery Wood</h2>

<p>At Nunnery Wood High School I worked with students who were either doing photography as part of their Art programme or were in the photography club. I asked them to find shapes in their teacher’s photos and trace them onto the screens in their cameras, using them as guides to line-up their views of the school, before photographing them. I also worked with a smaller group who were interested in the digital processes (focus stacking) I was abusing for the final work.</p>

<p>The artwork was created by merging each student’s (or pair of students’) photos on top of a single photograph from Kenya and then montaging them into an abstract stained-glass window effect.</p>

<p><img src="http://art.peteashton.com/assets/images/rotw2019-nunnery.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h2 id="tudor-grange">Tudor Grange</h2>

<p>At Tudor Grange School I was working with students without an art or photography background which gave a very different dynamic to Nunnery Wood. I lowered the expectations a bit and concentrated mostly on making and decorating the cameras and looking for patterns that they’d found in the teacher’s photos.</p>

<p>Because the camera obscuras had been central to the workshop I build the final artwork around them, as a frame for merges of their images as integrating photos of their decorated cameras. I also included some photos of the kids looking through them.</p>

<p><img src="http://art.peteashton.com/assets/images/rotw2019-tudor.jpg" alt="" /></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Photography" /><category term="Schools" /><category term="Workshops" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Thames Festival / British Council scheme twinning schools around the world using local rivers.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/rotw_2019_t.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/rotw_2019_t.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Jo Gane’s obscura research</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/bco-jogane/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jo Gane’s obscura research" /><published>2019-06-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-06-06T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Jo-Gane</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/bco-jogane/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.jogane.co.uk">Jo Gane</a>’s practice has been centred on early photographic techniques, such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daguerreotype">Daguerreotypes</a>, and in 2019 she was “exploring links between early Photography and Drawing inspired by the work of Victorian painter Frederick Henry Henshaw and early photographer George Shaw.”</p>

<p>She asked to borrow the <a href="http://bhamobscura.com">Birmingham Camera Obscura</a>, which lives flatpacked in my shed, so we set it up along the River Cole where Henshaw and Shaw made work and she made some sketches of a bridge while I answered questions from confused dog walkers.</p>

<p>If you’re an artist who’s interested in using the camera obscura as a tool in your practice, get in touch and we’ll see if we can work something out.</p>

<p><img src="http://art.peteashton.com/assets/images/jogane_bco_01.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><img src="http://art.peteashton.com/assets/images/jogane_bco_02.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><img src="http://art.peteashton.com/assets/images/jogane_bco_03.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/349546887" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; fullscreen" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Obscura" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Helping a fellow artist master the camera obscura as a drawing device.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/jogane_t.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/jogane_t.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>